<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">eLife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">02043</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Research article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Cell biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Systems analysis of the CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism in cyanobacteria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-9591"><name><surname>Mangan</surname><given-names>Niall M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa1">&#x2020;</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x2a;</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-2"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-3071"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>Michael P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2">&#x2a;</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-1"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-2"/><xref ref-type="other" rid="par-3"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line><named-content content-type="department">School of Engineering and Applied Sciences and Kavli Institute for Bionano Science and Technology</named-content></addr-line>, <institution>Harvard University</institution>, <addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Cambridge</named-content></addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>Ron</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff><institution>Weizmann Institute for Science</institution>, <country>Israel</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x2a;</label>For correspondence: <email>niallmm@gmail.com</email> (NMM);</corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x2a;</label>For correspondence: <email>brenner@seas.harvard.edu</email> (MPB)</corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="pa1"><label>&#x2020;</label><p>Mechanical Engineering/LMP, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA, United States</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e02043</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>04</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#xa9; 2014, Mangan and Brenner</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mangan and Brenner</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife02043.pdf"/><abstract><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.001</object-id><p>Cyanobacteria are photosynthetic bacteria with a unique CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism (CCM), enhancing carbon fixation. Understanding the CCM requires a systems level perspective of how molecular components work together to enhance CO<sub>2</sub> fixation. We present a mathematical model of the cyanobacterial CCM, giving the parameter regime (expression levels, catalytic rates, permeability of carboxysome shell) for efficient carbon fixation. Efficiency requires saturating the RuBisCO reaction, staying below saturation for carbonic anhydrase, and avoiding wasteful oxygenation reactions. We find selectivity at the carboxysome shell is not necessary; there is an optimal non-specific carboxysome shell permeability. We compare the efficacy of facilitated CO<sub>2</sub> uptake, CO<sub>2</sub> scavenging, and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport with varying external pH. At the optimal carboxysome permeability, contributions from CO<sub>2</sub> scavenging at the cell membrane are small. We examine the cumulative benefits of CCM spatial organization strategies: enzyme co-localization and compartmentalization.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.001">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.001</ext-link></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.002</object-id><title>eLife digest</title><p>Cyanobacteria are microorganisms that live in water and, like plants, they capture energy from the sun to convert carbon dioxide into sugars and other useful compounds. This process&#x2014;called photosynthesis&#x2014;releases oxygen as a by-product. Cyanobacteria were crucial in making the atmosphere of the early Earth habitable for other organisms, and they created the vast carbon-rich deposits that now supply us with fossil fuels. Modern cyanobacteria continue to sustain life on Earth by providing oxygen and food for other organisms, and researchers are trying to bioengineer cyanobacteria to produce alternative, cleaner, fuels.</p><p>Understanding how cyanobacteria can be as efficient as possible at harnessing sunlight to &#x2018;fix&#x2019; carbon dioxide into carbon-rich molecules is an important step in this endeavor. Carbon dioxide can readily pass through cell membranes, so instead cyanobacteria accumulate molecules of bicarbonate inside their cells. This molecule is then converted back into carbon dioxide by an enzyme found in specials compartments within cells called carboxysomes. The enzyme that fixes the carbon is also found in the carboxysomes. However, several important details in this process are not fully understood.</p><p>Here, Mangan and Brenner further extend a mathematical model of the mechanism that cyanobacteria use to concentrate carbon dioxide in order to explore the factors that optimize carbon fixation by these microorganisms. Carbon fixation is deemed efficient when there is more carbon dioxide in the carboxysome than the carbon-fixing enzyme can immediately use (which also avoids wasteful side-reactions that use oxygen instead of carbon dioxide). However, there should not be too much bicarbonate, otherwise the enzyme that converts it to carbon dioxide is overwhelmed and cannot take advantage of the extra bicarbonate.</p><p>Mangan and Brenner's model based the rates that carbon dioxide and bicarbonate could move in and out of the cell, and the rates that the two enzymes work, on previously published experiments. The model varied the location of the enzymes (either free in the cell or inside a carboxysome), and the rate at which carbon dioxide and bicarbonate could diffuse in and out of the carboxysome (the carboxysome's permeability). Mangan and Brenner found that containing the enzymes within a carboxysome increased the concentration of carbon dioxide inside the cell by an order of magnitude. The model also revealed the optimal permeability for the carboxysome outer-shell that would maximize carbon fixation.</p><p>In addition to being of interest to researchers working on biofuels, if the model can be adapted to work for plant photosynthesis, it may help efforts to boost crop production to feed the world&#x2019;s growing population.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.002">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.002</ext-link></p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><title>Author keywords</title><kwd>cyanobacteria</kwd><kwd>carboxysomes</kwd><kwd>carbon fixation</kwd><kwd>systems modeling</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>other</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="par-1"><funding-source>NSF Harvard Materials Research Science and Engineering Center</funding-source><award-id>DMR-0820484</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mangan</surname><given-names>Niall M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>Michael P</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-2"><funding-source>NSF Division of Mathematical Sciences</funding-source><award-id>DMS-0907985</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mangan</surname><given-names>Niall M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>Michael P</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="par-3"><funding-source>National Institute of General Medical Sciences    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.crossref.org/fundref/">FundRef identification ID: </ext-link> <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000057</named-content></funding-source><award-id>Grant GM068763 for National Centers of Systems Biology</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Mangan</surname><given-names>Niall M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>Michael P</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>elife-xml-version</meta-name><meta-value>0.7</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>Systems level modeling of cyanobacterial mechanism for concentrating carbon dioxide shows optimal organization and enzymatic activity for enhanced carbon fixation.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Intracellular compartments are critical for directing and protecting biochemical reactions. One of the simplest and most striking known examples of compartmentalization are the carboxysomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cannon et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Yeates et al., 2008</xref>) of cyanobacteria and other autotrophic proteobacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Savage et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Rosgaard et al., 2012</xref>). These small, 100&#x2212;200 nm compartments separate the principal reaction of the Calvin cycle, the RuBisCO catalyzed fixation of carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) into 3-phosphoglycerate, from the rest of the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cannon et al., 1991</xref>). CO<sub>2</sub> and oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) competitively bind as substrates of RuBisCO, and the reaction with O<sub>2</sub> produces phosphoglycolate, a waste product which must be recycled by the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Jordan and Ogren, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Tcherkez et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Savir et al., 2010</xref>). To maximize carboxylation and minimize oxygenation, the carboxysome is believed to act as a diffusion barrier to CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reinhold et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Dou et al., 2008</xref>). There is much interest in the design and function of such compartments and whether they can be used to enhance carbon fixation in other organisms such as plants or to improve reaction rates in other metabolic systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Papapostolou and Howorka, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Agapakis et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Ducat and Silver, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Frank et al., 2013</xref>). Increased efficiency of biochemical reactions will lead to better yield in bioengineered bacterial systems, creating new possibilities for production of high-value products such as biofuels. Enhancing carbon fixation in plants or other organisms could lead to increased carbon sequestration, or crop yield.</p><p>The concentrating mechanism in cyanobacteria relies on the interaction of a number of well characterized components, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, transferring inorganic carbon from outside the cell into cytosol and carboxysomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Allen, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kaplan and Reinhold, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Badger and Price, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Price et al., 2007</xref>). Due to this mechanism, inorganic carbon concentration is elevated well above 200&#x2013;300 &#x3bc;M, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration required for saturating the RuBisCO. Additionally a high CO<sub>2</sub> concentration increases the ratio of CO<sub>2</sub> to O<sub>2</sub> so that carboxylation dominates over oxygenation. Concentrations of 20&#x2013;40 mM inorganic carbon, up to 4000-fold higher than external levels, have been observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sultemeyer et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Price et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kaplan and Reinhold, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Woodger et al., 2005</xref>). The bilipid outer and cell membranes are highly permeable to small uncharged molecules such as CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gutknecht et al., 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Missner et al., 2008</xref>), so instead the cell primarily accumulates the charged and less membrane soluble bicarbonate (HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Volokita et al., 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Price and Badger, 1989</xref>). Active transporters, both constitutive and inducible, bring HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Omata et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Price et al., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">2008</xref>), and mechanisms exist to actively convert CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> at the thylakoid and cell membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shibata et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Maeda et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Price et al., 2008</xref>). Once it passively diffuses into the carboxysome, HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> is rapidly brought into equilibrium with CO<sub>2</sub> by the enzyme carbonic anhydrase, resulting in the production of CO<sub>2</sub> near RuBisCO. Carbonic anhydrase is known to be localized on the interior side of the carboxysome shell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Cannon et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cot et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Long et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Yeates et al., 2008</xref>). The carboxysome shell must be permeable enough to allow HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and 3-phosphoglycerate to readily diffuse in and out. The function of this system and its ability to concentrate inorganic carbon depends on the interplay between these various molecular components. Without a model, flux measurements cannot determine the components relative roles in enhancing the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome. To date, it has not been possible to directly measure the partitioning of the internal carbon concentration in the cytosol and carboxysomes. We wish to characterize the distribution of internal carbon. Visualizations of the location of the carboxysomes with fluorescent microscopy in <italic>S. elongatus</italic> PCC7942 demonstrated that the carboxysomes are evenly spaced along the centerline of the cell, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Savage et al., 2010</xref>), raising the question of how spatial organization, beyond simple partitioning, changes the efficacy of the system.<fig id="fig1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.003</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Schematic of the CCM in cyanobacteria.</title><p>Outer and cell membranes (in black), as well as, thylakoid membranes where the light reactions take place (in green) are treated together. Carboxysomes are shown as four hexagons evenly spaced along the centerline of the cell. The model treats a spherically symmetric cell, with one carboxysome at the center. Active HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport into the cell is indicated (in light blue), as well as active conversion from CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> at the membranes, sometimes called &#x2018;facilitated uptake&#x2019; or &#x2018;scavenging&#x2019; (in orange). Both CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> can leak in and out of the cell, with CO<sub>2</sub> leaking out much more readily. Both species passively diffuse across the carboxysome shell. Carbonic anhydrase (red) and RuBisCO (blue) are contained in the carboxysomes and facilitate reactions as shown.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.003">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.003</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043f001"/></fig></p><p>The goal of this study is to further develop a mathematical model of the CCM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reinhold et al., 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Fridlyand et al., 1996</xref>) that uses recent experimental progress on the CCM to untangle the relative roles of the different molecular components, and predict the region of parameter space where efficient carbon fixation occurs. We are considering conditions where CO<sub>2</sub> is limiting (15 &#x3bc;M external inorganic carbon) and, for the moment, ignore other biological pressures. In this context, efficient carbon fixation requires two conditions: First, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration must be high enough that RuBisCO is saturated, and the competitive reaction with O<sub>2</sub> is negligible. We emphasize that for the oxygenation reaction to be negligible the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration should be higher than needed to merely saturate RuBisCO. Secondly, the carbonic anhydrase within the carboxysome must be unsaturated, so that extra energy isn't wasted transporting unused HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the cell.</p><p>Examination of the system performance with varying expression levels of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transporters, carboxysome permeability, and conversion from CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, reveals a parameter window where these conditions are simultaneously satisfied. We comment on the relation of this window to measured carbon pools, carbon fixation rates, and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transporters. We find that the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration in the cytosol is constant across the cell, set by the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport and leakage rates, and depends very little on the carboxysome permeability. The carboxysome permeability does, however, set how the CO<sub>2</sub> is partitioned between the carboxysome and cytosol. At optimal carboxysome permeability, HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> diffusion into the carboxysome is fast enough to supply inorganic carbon for fixation, but the rate of CO<sub>2</sub> leakage out of the carboxysome is low. We explore the fluxes from CO<sub>2</sub> facilitated uptake and scavenging with varying ratios of external CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>. Finally we discuss the proportion the carbon concentration comes from different methods of spatial organization such as co-localization, encapsulation, and spatial location of carboxysomes. Concentration of carbonic anhydrase increases the maximum rate of reaction for carbonic anhydrase per volume, causing carbonic anhydrase to saturate at a higher level of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, and achieve an order of magnitude higher local CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations. Encapsulation of the reactions in an optimally permeable carboxysome shell achieves another order of magnitude of CO<sub>2</sub> concentration.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Reaction diffusion model</title><p>We present our mathematical model, which captures all aspects of the CCM as described above. This model is an expansion of previously developed models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Reinhold et al., 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Fridlyand et al., 1996</xref>). Our three dimensional model of the CCM solves for both the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration throughout the a spherical cell. We solve this model numerically and analytically at steady state for three different spatial organizations of carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO in the cell (Figure 6): enzymes distributed evenly throughout the cell, enzymes localized to the center of the cell but not encapsulated (as they would be on a scaffold), enzymes encapsulated in a carboxysome. We compare the effects of these scenarios in the discussion section, and for now consider a spherical cell of radius <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub> &#x3d; 0.5 &#x3bc;m with a single spherical carboxysome of radius <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 50 nm containing RuBisCO and carbonic anhydrase. Numerical computations are carried out with finite difference methods in MATLAB. The details of analytic solutions are given in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Supplementary file 1</xref>.</p><p>We include the effects of 3D diffusion, active transport and leakage through the cell membrane, and reactions with carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO. In the carboxysome (<italic>r</italic> &#x3c; <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>), the equations governing the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub>, here H and C respectively, are<disp-formula id="equ1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2207;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CA</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Rub</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2207;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CA</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where here <italic>D</italic> is the diffusion constant, and <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>CA</italic></sub> is the carbonic anhydrase reaction, and <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>Rub</italic></sub> is the RuBisCO reaction. The carbonic anhydrase reactions follows reversible Michaelis&#x2013;Menten kinetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kaplan and Reinhold, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Price et al., 2007</xref>),<disp-formula id="equ3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CA</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ba</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ca</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ca</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ba</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ba</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ca</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ca</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ba</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ca</italic></sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ba</italic></sub> are hydration and dehydration rates, proportional to the local carbonic anhydrase concentration. <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>ca</italic></sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>ba</italic></sub> are the concentration at which hydration and dehydration are half maximum. The RuBisCO reaction follows Michaelis&#x2013;Menten kinetics with competitive binding with O<sub>2</sub>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2032;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Here <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub> is the maximum rate of carbon fixation and <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> is the apparent half maximum concentration value, which has been modified to include competitive binding with O<sub>2</sub>, <italic>O</italic>. <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the dissociation constant of <italic>O</italic><sub>2</sub> with the RuBisCO and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf3"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2032;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the half maximum concentration with no <italic>O</italic><sub>2</sub> present. RuBisCO also requires ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate, the substrate which <italic>CO</italic><sub>2</sub> reacts with to produce 3-phosphoglycolate. Under CO<sub>2</sub> limiting conditions it has been shown that there is sufficient ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate to saturate all RuBisCO active sites, and the reaction rates are independent of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Mayo et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Whitehead et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>In the cytosol there is no carbonic anhydrase or RuBisCO activity, so <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>CA</italic></sub> &#x3d; 0 and <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>Rub</italic></sub> &#x3d; 0, and there is only diffusion of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>. We do not include the natural, but slow, interconversion of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> in the cytosol. This assumption is a good one given that the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration is known to be held out of equilibrium in the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Volokita et al., 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Price and Badger, 1989</xref>). In agreement with this experimental observation, we find that all the other processes effecting the concentration of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> in the cytosol happen much faster than the natural interconversion.</p><p>Boundary conditions proscribe the inorganic carbon fluxes into the cell and the diffusion across the carboxysome boundary. We treat the inorganic carbon fluxes at cell and thylakoid membranes together. At this cell boundary, there is passive leakage of both CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>: the velocity of CO<sub>2</sub> across the cell membrane, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf4"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is about 1000-fold higher than that of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf5"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, due to the lower permeability of the membrane to charged molecules. To account for active import of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, we combine the total HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> flux, <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, from all HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transporters. These transporters include BCT1 (encoded by cpm), which is thought to be powered by ATP; and BicA and SbtA which are thought to be symporters between HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and Na<sup>&#x2b;</sup>, driven by the highly controlled electrochemical gradient for Na<sup>&#x2b;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Omata et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Price et al., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">2008</xref>). Additionally, there are two complexes NDH-1<sub>3</sub> and NDH-1<sub>4</sub> responsible for converting CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>. This conversion is thought to either decrease CO<sub>2</sub>, creating a gradient across the membranes and &#x2018;facilitating uptake&#x2019; of CO<sub>2</sub>, or &#x2018;scavenge&#x2019; CO<sub>2</sub> which has escaped from the carboxysome. These are localized to the thylakoid and possibly the plasma membrane. They have been linked to the photosynthetic linear and cyclic electron transport chain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Shibata et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Maeda et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Price et al., 2008</xref>). It has been proposed that electron transport drives the formation of local alkaline pockets where CO<sub>2</sub> more rapidly converts to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>. We simply describe the conversion with a maximal reaction rate <italic>&#x3b1;</italic>, and concentration of half maximal activity of <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>&#x3b1;</italic></sub>. Combining these effects, the boundary condition setting diffusive flux of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub> at the cell membrane is<disp-formula id="equ4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="m4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="m5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the subscript <italic>cytosol</italic> and <italic>out</italic> indicate we are taking the concentration immediately inside and outside the cell boundary respectively. The diffusion constant times partial derivatives with respect to the radial coordinate, <italic>r</italic>, define the diffusive flux at the membrane.</p><p>The carboxysome shell is composed of proteins with a radius <italic>R</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x2248; 50 nm. As of yet, there have been no direct measurements of the carboxysome permeability to small molecules. Using the carboxysome geometry, we can calculate an upper bound for the diffusive velocity across the carboxysome shell, which is directly related to the carboxysome permeability. Crystal structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Yeates et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cheng et al., 2008</xref>) show the surface has approximately <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>pores</italic></sub> &#x3d; 4800 small pores with radius <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>pore</italic></sub>&#x2248;0.35 nm, and thickness <italic>l</italic> &#x3d; 1.8 nm. If <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> is the characteristic velocity that small molecules pass through the shell, these numbers imply the upper bound for diffusive transport <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3c;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03C0;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x03C0;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This calculation is done by taking the probability that a molecule will encounter a pore on the carboxysome shell <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf7"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#xd7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>pore</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>surface</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>area</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>carboxysome</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>surface</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>area</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and multipling it by the speed a small molecule will diffuse through the length of the pore (<italic>D</italic>/<italic>l</italic>). Since it does not take into account any charge effects, which would add an additional energy barrier, it is an upper bound. Although there has been much speculation that the positively charged pores might enhance diffusion of negatively charged HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cheng et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Dou et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Yeates et al., 2008</xref>), here we explore the simplest assumption, that both HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub> have the same permeability. Namely, the boundary conditions at the carboxysome shell are<disp-formula id="equ6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="m6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">carboxysome</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="equ7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="m7"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2202;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">carboxysome</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>We will vary <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> (henceforth called carboxysome permeability, although it is a velocity) within our model and see that there is a range of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> where the CCM is effective even with <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> identical for CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Analysis of model: finding functional parameter space</title><p>Now that we have defined our model, we wish to find the range of parameters where efficient carbon fixation occurs. In what follows, we fix the enzymatic rates, cell membrane permeability, and diffusion constant as reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gutknecht et al., 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Jordan and Ogren, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Heinhorst et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Missner et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1 tbl2">Tables 1 and 2</xref>). Note that full analytic solutions are available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1-data">Supplementary file 1</xref> sections S3 and S4, so the effect of varying these parameters can be analyzed. We consider the efficacy of the CCM as a function of <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, the flux of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the cell, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, the carboxysome permeability, and the parameters (<italic>&#x3b1;</italic>, <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>&#x3b1;</italic></sub>) governing the <italic>CO</italic><sub>2</sub> facilitated uptake mechanism. Both <italic>&#x3b1;</italic> and <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> can be regulated by the organism and vary depending on environmental conditions, whereas the carboxysome permeability, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, is the parameter with the largest uncertainty and debate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cannon et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cheng et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Yeates et al., 2008</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.004</object-id><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Parameter values chosen for main set of simulations, unless otherwise indicated</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.004">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.004</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Parameter</th><th>Definition</th><th>Value</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>H</italic><sub><italic>out</italic></sub></td><td>concentration of bicarbonate outside the cell</td><td>14 &#xb5;M<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">&#x2a;</xref></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Price et al., 2008</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C</italic><sub><italic>out</italic></sub></td><td>concentration of carbon dioxide outside of cell</td><td>0.14 &#xb5;M<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">&#x2a;</xref></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Price et al., 2008</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td><italic>D</italic></td><td>diffusion constant of small molecules, <italic>CO</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub> and <italic>HCO</italic><sub><italic>3</italic></sub><sup><italic>&#x2212;</italic></sup></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf8"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cm</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Fridlyand et al., 1996</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf9"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>permeability of cell membrane to <italic>CO</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub></td><td>0.3 <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf10"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gutknecht et al., 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Missner et al., 2008</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf11"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>permeability of cell membrane to <italic>CO</italic><sub><italic>2</italic></sub></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf12"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#xd7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gutknecht et al., 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Missner et al., 2008</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td><italic>R</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub></td><td>radius of carboxysome</td><td>5 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup> cm</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Schmid et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cheng et al., 2008</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td><italic>R</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub></td><td>radius of bacteria</td><td>5 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup> cm</td><td>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Savage et al., 2010</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td><italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub></td><td><italic>HCO</italic><sub><italic>3</italic></sub><sup><italic>&#x2212;</italic></sup> transport rate resulting in 30 mM cytosolic HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> pool</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf13"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">&#x2a;</xref></td><td>calculated</td></tr><tr><td><italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub></td><td>optimal carboxysome permeability</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf14"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#xd7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">&#x2a;</xref></td><td>calculated</td></tr><tr><td><italic>V</italic><sub><italic>cell</italic></sub></td><td>cell volume</td><td>5.2 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup> &#x3bc;L</td><td>calculated</td></tr><tr><td><italic>SA</italic><sub><italic>cell</italic></sub></td><td>cell surface area</td><td>3 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;8</sup> cm<sup>2</sup></td><td>calculated</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>&#x2a;</label><p>these parameters are varied in the text, but these values are used unless noted otherwise.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.005</object-id><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Table comparing enzymatic rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sultemeyer et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Woodger et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Heinhorst et al., 2006</xref>)</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.005">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.005</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Enzyme reaction</th><th>active sites</th><th><italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cut</italic></sub> <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf15"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><italic>V</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub> in cell <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf16"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03BC;</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><italic>V</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub> in carboxysome <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf17"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03BC;</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><italic>K</italic><sub><italic>1/2</italic></sub> [&#xb5;M]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>carbonic anhydrase hydration</td><td align="char" char=".">80</td><td>8 &#xd7; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td>1.1&#xd7;10<sup>4</sup></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">2 &#xd7; 10<sup>8</sup></td><td>3.2 &#xd7; 10<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td>carbonic anhydrase dehydration</td><td align="char" char=".">80</td><td>4.6 &#xd7; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td>9.5&#xd7;10<sup>4</sup></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">1.7 &#xd7; 10<sup>8</sup></td><td>9.3 &#xd7; 10<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td>RuBisCO carboxylation</td><td align="char" char=".">2160</td><td>26</td><td>103</td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">1.7 &#xd7; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td>270</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>V</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub> in cell and carboxysome refer to the volumetric reaction rate assuming the enzymes are distributed through cellout the entire cell or only carboxysome. <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ba</italic></sub> (<italic>V</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub> for carbonic anhydrase dehydration) is estimated by assuming <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>eq</italic></sub> &#x3d; 5 and using parameters found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Heinhorst et al. (2006)</xref>. <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ca</italic></sub> is <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub> for carbonic anhydrase hydration. Similarly, <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>ba</italic></sub>, and <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>ca</italic></sub> are <italic>K</italic><sub>1/2</sub> for dehydration and hydration respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>For any given pair of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, we ask whether the CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism is effective, using the criteria of saturating RuBisCO, reducing oxidation reactions, and not increasing the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration beyond carbonic anhydrase saturation. Our central result is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, which shows the range of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> where these conditions are met, assuming that there is no facilitated uptake, <italic>&#x3b1;</italic> &#x3d; 0.The blue shaded region shows where RuBisCO is unsaturated, and the red shaded region shows where carbonic anhydrase is saturated. There is a crescent shaped region between these regions, where the CCM is effective according to our criteria. In the white region oxygenation reactions happen at a rate of greater than 1%. In the green shaded region oxygenation reactions occur at a rate of less than 1%. Within the white and green regions the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome varies greatly.<fig-group><fig id="fig2" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.006</object-id><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Phase space for HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport, <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, and carboxysome permeability <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>.</title><p>Plotted are the parameter values at which the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reaches some critical value. The left most line (dark blue) indicates for what values of <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome would half-saturate RuBisCO (<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>). The middle line (light blue) indicates the parameter values which would result in a CO<sub>2</sub> concentration where 99% of all RuBisCO reactions are carboxylation reactions and only 1% are oxygenation reactions when O<sub>2</sub> concentration is 260 &#xb5;M. The right most (red) line indicates the parameter values which result in carbonic anyhdrase saturating. Here &#x3b1; &#x3d; 0, so there is no CO<sub>2</sub> scavenging or facilitated uptake. The dotted line (grey) shows the <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> values, where the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration in the cytosol is 30 mM. The HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration in the cytosol does not vary appreciably with <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> in this parameter regime, and reaches 30 mM at <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. All other parameters, such as reaction rates are held fixed and the value can be found in the <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1 tbl2">Table 1 and 2</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.006">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.006</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043f002"/></fig><fig id="fig2s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.007</object-id><label>Figure 2&#x2014;figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>Phase space for HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>transport and carboxysome permeability.</title><p>Solid lines show lines of constant CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome for <inline-formula ><mml:math id="inf69"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cm</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, or the diffusion constant of small molecule in water. Dashed lines show the same lines of constant CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, bur for <inline-formula ><mml:math id="inf70"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cm</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, or the diffusion constant of a small molecule in a 60% sucrose solution.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.007">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.007</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043fs001"/></fig><fig id="fig2s2" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.008</object-id><label>Figure 2&#x2014;figure supplement 2.</label><caption><title>Effect of CO2 scavenging or facilitated uptake on phase space for HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>transport, <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, and carboxysome permeability, <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>.</title><p>Plotted are the parameter values at which CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reaches some critical value. The left most line (dark blue) indicates for what values of <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> the CO<sub>2</sub>concentration in the carboxysome would saturate RuBisCO. The middle line (light blue) indicates the parameter values which would result in a CO<sub>2</sub> concentration where 99% of all RuBisCO reactions are carboxylation reactions and only 1% are oxygenation reactions when O<sub>2</sub> concentration is 260 &#xb5;M. The right most (red) line indicatesthee parameter values which result in carbonic anyhdrase saturating. Here <inline-formula ><mml:math id="inf71"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>(solid lines) and <inline-formula ><mml:math id="inf72"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>(dashed line), showing the effect of CO<sub>2</sub> scavenging or facilitated uptake on the phase space. All other parameters, such as reaction rates are held fixed and the value can be found <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.008</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043fs002"/></fig></fig-group></p><p>The lines dividing the regions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> are lines of constant carboxysomal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> parameter space. The dark blue line is where CO<sub>2</sub> &#x3d; K<sub>m</sub>, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration for half maximum RuBisCO reactions. The light blue line indicates parameter values resulting in the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>99%</sub>) where rate of oxygenation reactions is 1% for O<sub>2</sub> concentration of 260 &#x3bc;M. Varying carboxysome permeability, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> values, require more or less HCO<sub>3</sub> transport, <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, to achieve the same carboxysomal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration.</p><p>We can calculate an amplification factor for the <italic>C</italic><sub>99%</sub> line of constant carboxysomal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration as <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">carboxysome</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>133</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Any combination of <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> which produce <italic>C</italic> &#x3d; <italic>C</italic><sub>99%</sub>, make 133 times more CO<sub>2</sub> available in the carboxysome than there is total inorganic carbon outside the cell. Generally, increasing HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport, below the carbonic anhydrase saturation point results in higher CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Varying HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport saturates enzymes</title><p>The basic physics of the phase diagram <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> follows from examining how CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> in the carboxysome change as <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> is varied. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> shows the response to varying <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#xd7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (the optimal value in Figure 4).<fig-group><fig id="fig3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.009</object-id><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Numerical solution (diamonds and circles) and analytic solutions (carbonic anhydrase unsaturated, solid lines, and saturated, dashed lines) correspond well.</title><p>HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport is varied, and all other system parameters are held constant. The CO<sub>2</sub> concentration above which RuBisCO is saturated is <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> (grey dashed line). The CO<sub>2</sub> concentration where the oxygen reaction error rate will be 1% is <italic>C</italic><sub>99%</sub> (grey dash-dotted line). The transition between carbonic anyhdrase being unsatruated and saturated happens where the two analytic solutions meet (where the dashed and solid red lines meet). Below a critical value of transport, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the level of transport is lower than the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leaking through the cell membrane.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.009">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.009</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043f003"/></fig><fig id="fig3s1" position="float" specific-use="child-fig"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.010</object-id><label>Figure 3&#x2014;figure supplement 1.</label><caption><title>No effect of localizing carbonic anhydrase to the shell of the carboxysome.</title><p>We assume the same amount of carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO activity for each simulation and compare the case with the enzymes evenly distributed throughout the carboxysome to the case where the carbonic anhydrase is localized to the inner carboxysome shell. The (&#x2212;.&#x2212;) lines are for no organization and (x) for localization with <inline-formula ><mml:math id="inf73"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The (&#x2026;) lines are for no organization and (o) are for localization with <inline-formula ><mml:math id="inf74"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.010">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.010</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043fs003"/></fig></fig-group><fig id="fig4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.011</object-id><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> in the carboxysome with varying carboxysome permeability.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Numerical solution (diamonds and circles) and analytic solutions (carbonic anhydrase unsaturated, solid lines, and saturated, dashed lines) correspond well. On all plots CO<sub>2</sub> (red circle) &#x3c; HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> (blue diamond). Concentration in the cell along the radius, <italic>r</italic>, with carboxysome permeability <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<bold>B</bold>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf23"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<bold>C</bold>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf24"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<bold>D</bold>). Grey dotted lines in (<bold>B</bold>), (<bold>C</bold>), (<bold>D</bold>) indicate location of the carboxysome shell boundary. The transition from low CO<sub>2</sub> at high permeability (<bold>D</bold>) to maximum CO<sub>2</sub> concentration at optimal permeability (<bold>C</bold>) occurs at <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf25"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2a;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. At low carboxysome permeability (<bold>B</bold>) HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> diffusion into the carboxysome is slower than consumption. For all subplots <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf26"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf27"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Qualitative results remain the same with varying <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, increasing <italic>&#x3b1;</italic> will increase the gradient of CO<sub>2</sub> across the cell as CO<sub>2</sub> is converted to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> at the cell membrane.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.011">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.011</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043f004"/></fig></p><p>When <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> is low, the ratio of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> is constant, set by the chemical equilibrium at a given pH. In this case the rate of the carbonic anhydrase reaction is much faster than diffusion within the carboxysome, so that <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf28"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Unlike the uncatalyzed interconversion of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> in the cytosol, carbonic anhydrase brings the concentrations in the carboxysome to equilibrium very quickly. The chemical equilibrium is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf29"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, for pH around 7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">DeVoe and Kistiakowsky, 1961</xref>), so that HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>&#x3e;CO<sub>2</sub> in the carboxysome. Increased pH would increase <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>eq</italic></sub> and the proportion of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, while decreased pH would decrease <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>eq</italic></sub> and the proportion of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>. Such variations do not substantially effect the subsequent discussion and mechanisms, although they will change the absolute values of CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome.</p><p>The <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> dashed line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> shows the CO<sub>2</sub> level above which RuBisCO reaction is saturated: this gives the RuBisCO saturated (blue) boundary in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>. We have similarly marked the concentration <italic>C</italic><sub>99%</sub> where there is a 1% oxygen reaction error rate with a dash-doted line.</p><p>At higher levels, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration no longer increases with increasing <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, because the carbonic anhydrase is saturated. The saturated regime occurs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> when <italic>H</italic><sub><italic>carboxysome</italic></sub>&#x3e;<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>ba</italic></sub>, so that increasing <italic>H</italic><sub><italic>carboxysome</italic></sub> (controlled directly by <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>) no longer increases the rate of production of <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>carboxysome</italic></sub>. This transition from unsaturated to saturated carbonic anhydrase defines the line for the carbonic anhydrase saturated region in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Carboxysome permeability has optimal value</title><p>For each line of constant concentration in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> there is an optimal permeability value, where the least HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport is required to achieve the same CO<sub>2</sub> concentration. The optimal permeability value shifts downward with increasing CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (compare light and dark blue curves). For <italic>C</italic><sub>99%</sub> the optimal permeability is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf30"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#xd7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, below the calculated upper bound: <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf31"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> obtained above from the carboxysome structure. To further understand the effect of permeability, we examine the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome for varying carboxysome permeabilities and a fixed HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport rate in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, shows that there is a broad range of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> where the CCM has maximal efficacy. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> shows the distribution of inorganic carbon throughout the cell when the permeability is low (B), optimal (C), and high (D). At high permeability, the CO<sub>2</sub> produced in the carboxysome rapidly leaks out of the carboxysome, and the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the cytosol, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>, is relatively high. When the carboxysome permeability decreases to near the optimal value, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4D</xref>, the carboxysome traps CO<sub>2</sub>, and the cytosolic levels are lower, decreasing leakage out of the cell. This transition occurs when diffusion across the cell (and carboxysome) takes a shorter time than diffusion through the carboxysome shell; or the CO<sub>2</sub> in the carboxysome is effectively partitioned from the CO<sub>2</sub> in the cell.</p><p>If the carboxysome permeability is below optimal, diffusion of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the carboxysome cannot keep up with consumption from RuBisCO. The existence of an optima requires RuBisCO consumption to be low enough that there is a <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> where the cytosol and carboxysome are partitioned, but HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> diffusion in can keep up. When such an optima exists, the carboxysome permeability can improve the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome without any special selectivity between HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub>. The location and concentrating power of the optimal regime, is dependent on the size of the cell and the membrane permeabilities to CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Are the fluxes and concentrations reasonable?</title><p>While we have solved our model to describe a vast parameters space it is instructive to compare the fluxes and concentrations we find within our optimal parameter space (the green region in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>) to actual numbers. At low external inorganic carbon conditions, internal inorganic carbon pools due to CCM activity are regularly measured as high as <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> &#x3d; 30<italic>mM</italic>. The inorganic carbon is predominantly in the form of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, and measurements do not distinguish between the cytosol and carboxysome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Sultemeyer et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Price et al., 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kaplan and Reinhold, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Woodger et al., 2005</xref>). In our model, we find that the cytosolic HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration is 30 mM when <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, over a wide range of the carboxysome permeability (indicated as the dashed grey line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> we can also see that the cytosolic HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration is the dominate form of inorganic carbon in the cell at <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf33"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We examine the fate of the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transported into the cell in terms of the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leaking out, CO<sub>2</sub> leaking out, CO<sub>2</sub> fixation or carboxylation, and O<sub>2</sub> fixation or oxygenation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.012</object-id><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Fate of carbon brought into the cell for <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf34"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf35"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#xd7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.012">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.012</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>formula</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf36"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th>% of flux</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf37"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">3.3 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td/></tr><tr><td>HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leakage</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf38"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">3.2 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">96.6</td></tr><tr><td>CO<sub>2</sub> leakage</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf39"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">3.1</td></tr><tr><td>carboxylation</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf40"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">9 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">0.3</td></tr><tr><td>oxygenation</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf41"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">3 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;9</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>For cells grown under low inorganic carbon conditions net HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> fluxes (transport&#x2013;leakage) are measured 10<sup>5</sup> <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf42"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pmol</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mgChl</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with CO<sub>2</sub> net flux being slightly lower but the same order of magnitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Badger et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Whitehead et al., 2014</xref>). High external inorganic carbon conditions produce slightly higher net HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Tchernov et al., 1997</xref>). Assuming chlorophyll per cell volume of around <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf43"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mgChl</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>cell</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for cells of our size we can convert this into a flux of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf44"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Keren et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Whitehead et al., 2014</xref>). The net HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> flux for our model cell is <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf45"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, so we are about an order of magnitude too high. If we choose a HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport value one order of magnitude smaller, we will get net fluxes of the same order of magnitude as the measurements at the cost of slightly lower carboxylation rates and higher oxygenation rates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). This would also mean a lower internal HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> pool. Alternatively, the same internal HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> could be reached at a lower flux rate, if the external HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> is higher. We have chosen a dramatically low external inorganic carbon concentration, where the CCM is known to be up-regulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Price et al., 2008</xref>). The general results we present hold until the internal and external concentration are of the same order of magnitude, at which point the CCM is no longer necessary. Since the majority of the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport is balanced by HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leakage, we can find the transport rate needed to sustain a particular internal concentration by the simple formula: <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf46"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.<table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.013</object-id><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Fate of carbon brought into the cell for <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf47"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.07</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf48"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#xd7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.013">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.013</ext-link></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>formula</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf49"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th>% of flux</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf50"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">3.3 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td/></tr><tr><td>HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leakage</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf51"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">3.2 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">95.3</td></tr><tr><td>CO<sub>2</sub> leakage</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf52"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">out</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cytosol</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">9 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">2.8</td></tr><tr><td>carboxylation</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf53"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">6 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">1.7</td></tr><tr><td>oxygenation</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="inf54"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2b;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="char" char="&#xd7;">2 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;8</sup></td><td align="char" char=".">0.07</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>While we can compare the net fluxes, we have not found direct experimental evidence for the absolute HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> uptake rate. To determine whether this HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport rate is reasonable we perform a back of the envelope calculation. Our simulated cell has a flux of 2 &#xd7; 10<sup>7</sup>molecules/s. Assuming the rate of transport per transporter of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf55"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>molecules</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and our cell&#x2019;s surface area this requires about <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf56"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>transporters</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03BC;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This is actually not that far off from the number of ATP synthase complexes on the thylakoid membrane in spinach, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf57"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>700</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>complexes</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x03BC;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Miller and Staehelin, 1979</xref>), although it is still quite high.</p><p>According to our calculation only around 1 % of the inorganic carbon transported into the cell is fixed into 3-phosophoglycerate. The conclusion that about 99% of inorganic carbon transported into the cell is lost through leakage challenges the assumption that the 3 ATP and 2 NADPH used during the Calvin-Benson-Bassham cycle is the dominant energy expenditure. If it holds true, then cyanobacteria invest much more energy in inorganic carbon uptake than was previously understood. Even in this highly CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating regime, 5 &#xd7; 10<sup>4</sup> 2-phosophoglycolate are produced per second. Cyanobacteria have been shown to have multiple pathways for recycling 2-phosophoglycolate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Hackenberg et al., 2009</xref>). Our system fixes CO<sub>2</sub> at a rate of 0.14 <italic>pg</italic>/<italic>hr</italic>. Given the volume of our cell, and the fact that between 115&#x2013;300 fg/&#x3bc;m<sup>3</sup> of carbon are needed to produce a new cyanobacterial cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Mahlmann et al., 2008</xref>) we need between 0.1 and 0.3 picograms of carbon per cell. At the higher flux rate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>) this means that a cell could replicate every 1&#x2013;2 hr, so faster than cyanobacteria replicate. The lower flux rate (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>) would produce fix enough CO<sub>2</sub> for the cell to replicate every 8 to 21 hr, which is similar to the division times of cyanobacteria.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Concentration profiles of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> across the cell</title><p>At <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf58"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, varying the carboxysome permeability changes how the available inorganic carbon is partitioned between the carboxysome and cytosol, thereby setting the carboxysomal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. Strikingly, the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration is constant across the cytosol. This is because the cell membranes have low permeability to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>; thus, the rate of escape is slow and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> equilibrates across the cell. A consequence of this flat HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> profile is that the carboxysome experiences the same HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration, independent of its position in the cell. This means the incoming inorganic carbon source for the carboxysome system is invariant with the position of the carboxysome in the cell.</p><p>In contrast, there is a gradient in CO<sub>2</sub> concentration across the cell when the carboxysome permeability is at or above the optimum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C,D</xref>). The cell membrane is more permeable to CO<sub>2</sub>. The gradient means that the CO<sub>2</sub> leakage out of the cell affects the CO<sub>2</sub> leakage out of the carboxysome. Moving the carboxysome close to the cell membrane increases the leakage rate of CO<sub>2</sub> out of the carboxysome. Notably, in <italic>S. elongatus</italic> the carboxysomes are located along the center line of the cell, away from the cell membranes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Savage et al., 2010</xref>). The spatial profiles of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub> give no hint as to why the carboxysomes are spaced apart from one another. Since the gradient in HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> is flat, there is no competition between the carboxysomes for HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> (the main incoming source of inorganic carbon). In fact, since the local concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> is higher near a carboxysome, nearby carboxysomes would &#x201d;feed&#x201d; each other CO<sub>2</sub>. As has been shown, such clumping would reduce the probability of distributing carboxysomes equitably to daughter cells, possibly counteracting any benefit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Savage et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>The concentration in the carboxysome is basically constant, because the carboxysome is so small that diffusion across it takes very little time. A consequence of this is that the organization of the reactions in the carboxysome does not effect the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3&#x2014;figure supplement 1</xref>). Therefore, the localization of the carbonic anhydrase to the inner carboxysome shell seems to have no effect on the CCM. It has been suggested that diffusion in the carboxysome should be slower, since the carboxysome is packed with RuBisCO. One proposed consequence of slower diffusion in the carboxysome is that it could trap CO<sub>2</sub>, making a low carboxysome permeability unnecessary. We have tested this hypothesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s1">Figure 2&#x2014;figure supplement 1</xref>), and find that assuming the diffusion constant one would expect for small molecules in a 60% sucrose solution (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf59"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x2009;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), does reduce the optimal carboxysome permeability. However, for any carboxysome permeability a higher HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport rate is needed to achieve the same carboxsomal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration. So, if the diffusion is slower in the carboxysome it does not aid the CCM. Even at this slower diffusion, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration across the carboxysome is flat.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Benefit of CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> conversion: facilitated uptake or scavenging of CO<sub>2</sub></title><p>We investigate the effect of CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> conversion at the thylakoid and cell membranes (combined in the model). Increasing conversion, <italic>&#x3b1;</italic> &#x3e;0, can facilitate uptake of CO<sub>2</sub> from outside the cell and scavenge CO<sub>2</sub> escaped from the carboxysome. Facilitated uptake results in saturating both carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO at a lower level of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport. Scavenging broadens the range of carboxysome permeability which will effectively separate the inorganic carbon pools in the carboxysome and outside. Scavenging decreases the concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> in the cytosol, so a more permeable carboxysome can still result in a low leakage rate of inorganic carbon out of the cell (more of the inorganic carbon in the cytosol is in the form of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> which leaks out less readily). However, neither of these effects is particularly strong in our current range of reaction rates, and cell membrane permeability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2s2">Figure 2&#x2014;figure supplement 2</xref>).</p><p>The relative effects of these two mechanisms depends on the external CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentrations. In saltwater environments the pH is near 8 and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> is the predominant inorganic carbon source. While external pH is not explicitly treated in our model, we can account for changes to pH through the external inorganic carbon concentration. To be consistent with oceanic environment, thus far we have shown results for low external inorganic carbon concentrations of [CO<sub>2</sub>] &#x3d; 0.1 &#x3bc;M and [HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>] &#x3d; 14.9 &#x3bc;M. The effect of facilitated uptake, under these assumptions, is very small. In freshwater or under conditions of ocean acidification, where the pH could fall to 6 or lower, there can be a much larger proportion of CO<sub>2</sub> (&#x3e;50%). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> shows the absolute contribution of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport, facilitated CO<sub>2</sub> uptake, and CO<sub>2</sub> scavenging for varying proportions of external CO<sub>2</sub>. Even though we assume the same velocity of facilitated uptake and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport (<inline-formula><mml:math id="inf60"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x3b1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x3b1;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), facilitated uptake contributes less because it is limited by CO<sub>2</sub> diffusion across the membrane. At the same rates of transport the facilitated uptake mechanism only contributes more than active HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> if the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration is greater than 80% of external inorganic carbon. This is consistent with observations that oceanic cyanobacteria such as Prochlorococcus only seem to possess gene homologs for HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport systems, while other freshwater and estuarine cyanobacteria have gene homologs for both constitutive (NDH-1<sub>4</sub>) and inducible (NDH-1<sub>3</sub>) CO<sub>2</sub> uptake systems as well as inducible HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport systems (BicA, SbtA, and BCT1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Price, 2011</xref>).<fig id="fig5" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.014</object-id><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Size of the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> flux in one cell from varying sources, as the proportion of CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> outside the cell changes changes.</title><p>We show results for three carboxysome permeabilities, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>, and only the scavenging is effected. Total external inorganic carbon is 15 &#xb5;M, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf61"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf62"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. When the carboxysome permeability is larger than optimal, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf63"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, scavenging can contribute more than facilitated uptake at low external CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations. However, when the carboxysome permeability at or below our geometric bound, <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf64"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, scavenging is negligibly small. Unless there is very little HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> in the environment, HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport seems to be more efficient than CO<sub>2</sub> facilitated uptake.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.014">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.014</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043f005"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.015</object-id><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> achieved through various cellular organizations of enzymes, where we have selected the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport level such that the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration in the cytosol is <italic>30 mM</italic>.</title><p>O<sub>2</sub> concentration is 260 &#xb5;M. The oxygenation error rates, as a percent of total RuBisCO reactions are indicated on the concentration bars. The cellular organizations investigated are RuBisCO and carbonic anhydrase distributed throughout the entire cytosol, co-localizing RuBisCO and carbonic anhydrase on a scaffold at the center of the cell without a carboxysome shell, RuBisCO and carbonic anhydrase encapsulated in a carboxysome with high permeability at the center of the cell, and RuBisCO and carbonic anhydrase encapsulated in a carboxysome with optimal permeability at the center of the cell.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.015">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.015</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="elife02043f006"/></fig></p><p>Scavenging only contributes significantly to total incoming HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> when the carboxysome permeability is higher than optimal, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>, and does not contribute significantly below our caculated upper bound of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf65"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In these ranges for carboxysome permeability, there is very little CO<sub>2</sub> leaking out of the carboxysome into the cytosol, so there is very little CO<sub>2</sub> to scavenge, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>. The effect of scavenging is dependent on the cell membrane permeability to CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>.</p><p>Given that scavenging has no obvious affect on HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentrations, it is reasonable to wonder why this mechanism exists at all. One might assume that scavenging prevents leakage, but if the energy to bring a &#x2018;new&#x2019; HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> molecule from outside the cell is the same as the energy required to save an &#x2018;old&#x2019; CO<sub>2</sub> molecule from leaking out, there is no obvious advantage of preventing the leakage. It is possible that since the scavenging mechanism is associated with the electron transport chain of the light reactions of photosynthesis scavenging can be ramped up more easily when there is excess light energy. If this were the case, a comparison of <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf66"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf67"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x3d;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is deceiving and <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf68"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x03B1;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> could be much larger. It has been suggested that the cell uses this mechanism as a way to dissipate excess light energy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Tchernov et al., 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">2003</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Cellular organization</title><p>The most striking aspect of the CCM is the way that spatial organization is used to increase the efficacy of the reactions. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref> compares the effect of different enzymatic reaction organizations. Concentrating carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO to a small region in the center of the cell, on a scaffold for example, leads to an order of magnitude increase in the concentration of CO<sub>2</sub>. Localizing the carbonic anhydrase to a small volume concentrates it, increasing the maximum reaction rate per volume, <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ca</italic></sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ba</italic></sub>. A larger <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ba</italic></sub> increases the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration at which carbonic anhydrase is saturated allowing the mechanism to take advantage of a larger HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> flux, <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>. A small increase can be gained from encapsulating the enzymes in a permeable carboxysome shell and another order of magnitude is gained at the optimal permeability. At optimal carboxysome permeability, the CO<sub>2</sub> is effectively partitioned into the carboxysome and conversion can act only as facilitated uptake as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>.</p><p>Another advantage of localizing the enzymes in a small region at the center of the cell is separating carbonic anhydrase from the <italic>&#x3b1;</italic> (CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>) conversion mechanism, preventing a futile cycle. The futile cycle is most detrimental when the enzymes are distributed throughout the cytosol, and increases the oxygenation error rate by 10% (data not shown). Concentrating the enzymes away from the cell and thylakoid membranes, where conversion happens, removes this effect. With a carboxysome or scaffold the oxygenation rate is almost exactly the same with and without the <italic>&#x3b1;</italic> conversion mechanism. This is consistent with the previously shown detrimental effect of having active carbonic anhydrase free within the cytosol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Price and Badger, 1989</xref>). It would be impossible to keep the cytosol completely free from carbonic anhydrase enzyme, so there must be a way of activating it within the carboxysome only. Carbonic anhydrase is inactivated under reducing conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Pe&#xf1;a et al., 2010</xref>). Recently it was shown that carboxysomes oxidize after assembly, providing a way to keep carbonic anhydrase inactive until fully enclosed in a carboxysome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Chen et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Effects of pH</title><p>Cyanobacteria must regulate pH as almost all biochemical reactions are pH sensitive. We do not attempt to model this regulation or potential pH variation within the cell, however pH may be included implicitly in a couple ways. We have already explored the effect of varying external pH, and the effects of pH on carbonic anhydrase. Cytosolic pH would have little direct effect on the CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> levels since the non-enzymatic interconversion is very slow as previously discussed. The effect of internal pH could also be explored by varying the reaction rate of RuBisCO, which is pH sensitive. Varying the reaction rate of RuBisCO greatly could change the range where a non-specific carboxysome permeability can increase the concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> in the carboxysome. It would be unexpected that the RuBisCO rate be much faster than we assume, as we have assumed a rate on the high end. A lower RuBisCO rate would increase the range of effective carboxysome permeabilities. As previously mentioned it has been hypothesized that the CO<sub>2</sub> facilitated uptake mechanism functions by creating local alkaline pockets. Diffusion of hydrogen ions across the cell would be very fast, so it could be very difficult to to maintain local alkalinity. Whether such pH gradients are possible, is certainly a subject of future interest.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We have described and analyzed a model for the CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism in cyanobacteria. There exists a broad range of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport and carboxysome permeability values which result in effective CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome. This effective concentration parameter space is defined by CO<sub>2</sub> levels high enough to saturate RuBisCO and produce a favorable ratio of carboxylation to oxygenation reactions, but not so high as to saturate carbonic anhydrase (after which increasing HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport will not increase the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration). An optimal, non-specific carboxysome permeability exists, where HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> diffusion into the carboxysome is not substantially inhibited, but CO<sub>2</sub> leakage is minimal. HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentrations across the cell are flat and are predominately set by the transport rate in, and leakage out. We quantitatively compare the transport rates and concentrations we predict in our optimal parameter space, and find them to be in good agreement with experiment. We also comment on the effects of external pH on CO<sub>2</sub> versus HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> uptake mechanisms. Finally we describe the cumulative benefits of co-localization, encapsulation, and optimal carboxysome permeability on the CCM.</p><p>Further comparison of this model to experimental flux measurements, especially to determine the quantitative contributions of different transporters under different physiological conditions would be very interesting. Current solutions are for steady state at constant external concentration, but most gas exchange measurements, by necessity, measure the fluxes as the inorganic carbon is depleted in the media. The model could be modified to solve the time dependent problem with varying external inorganic carbon. As of yet the carboxysome permeability has not been measured directly, and it would be quite interesting to see how close it is to our &#x2018;optimal&#x2019; prediction.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Colleen Cavanaugh, Jeremy Gunarawenda and Pam Silver for important conversations. This research was supported by the National Science Foundation through the Harvard Materials Research Science and Engineering Center (DMR-0820484) and the Division of Mathematical Sciences (DMS-0907985). MPB is an Investigator of the Simons Foundation.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="conflict" id="conf1"><p>The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>NMM, Performed calculations, Conception and design, Analysis and interpretation of data, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>MPB, Oversaw and mentored research, Conception and design, Drafting or revising the article</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="SD1-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.016</object-id><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><caption><p>Mathematical derivation appendix. Mathematical derivations of analytic solutions for a spherical cell with reactions organized in a variety of ways. We present analytic solutions for the concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> a carboxysome located at the center of the cell. We derive analytic solutions assuming a number of different cases for the enzymatic rates in the carboxysome: RuBisCO reaction rate negligible with carbonic anhydrase saturated and unsaturated, RuBisCO reaction rate non-negligible with carbonic anhydrase unsaturated. Additionally we derive analytic solutions for the enzymatic reactions throughout the cell and localized to a scaffold without a carboxysome shell.</p><p><bold>DOI:</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.02043.016">http://dx.doi.org/10.7554/eLife.02043.016</ext-link></p></caption><media xlink:href="elife02043s001.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agapakis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Natural strategies for the spatial optimization of metabolism in synthetic biology</article-title>. <source>Nature Chemical Biology</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>535</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.975</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1984</year>. <article-title>Cyanobacterial cell inclusions</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Microbiology</source> <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.38.100184.000245</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmqvist</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1994</year>. <article-title>Measurement of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> fluxes in cyanobacteria and microalgae during steady-state photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Physiologia Plantarium</source> <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>536</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.1994.tb08811.x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanisms in cyanobacteria: molecular components and their diversity and evolution</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source> <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>622</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erg076</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradburne</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinhorst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <article-title>Microcompartments in prokaryotes: carboxysomes and related polyhedra</article-title>. <source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source> <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>5351</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5361</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.67.12.5351-5361.2001</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>English</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1991</year>. <article-title>In situ assay of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase in <italic>Thiobacillus neapolitanus</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source> <volume>173</volume>:<fpage>1565</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1568</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson-Mosher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Polka</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>The bacterial carbon-fixing organelle is formed by shell envelopment of preassembled cargo</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e76127</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076127</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobik</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Bacterial microcompartments: their properties and paradoxes</article-title>. <source>Bioessays: news and Reviews in Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1084</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1095</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.20830</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>So</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Espie</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>A multiprotein bicarbonate dehydration complex essential to carboxysome function in cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source> <volume>190</volume>:<fpage>936</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>945</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01283-07</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeVoe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kistiakowsky</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1961</year>. <article-title>The enzymatic kinetics of carbonic anhydrase from bovine and human erythrocytes</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source> <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>274</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>280</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja01463a004</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinhorst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Murin</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> fixation kinetics of <italic>Halothiobacilus neapolitanus</italic> mutant carboxysomes lacking carbonic anhydrase suggest the shell acts as a diffusional barrier for CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source> <volume>283</volume>:<fpage>10377</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10384</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M709285200</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ducat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Improving carbon fixation pathways</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Chemical Biology</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>344</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbpa.2012.05.002</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>Bacterial microcompartments moving into a synthetic biology world</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biotechnology</source> <volume>163</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>279</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2012.09.002</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fridlyand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>Quantitative evaluation of the role of a putative CO<sub>2</sub>-scavenging entity in the cyanobacterial CO<sub>2</sub>-concentrating mechanism</article-title>. <source>Bio Systems</source> <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>238</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0303-2647(95)01561-2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutknecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tosteson</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1977</year>. <article-title>Diffusion of carbon dioxide through lipid bilayer membranes: effects of carbonic anyhdrase, bicarbonate, and unstirred layers</article-title>. <source>The Journal of General Physiology</source> <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>779</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>794</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.69.6.779</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hackenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthijs</surname><given-names>HCP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittink</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauwe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Photorespiratory 2-phosphoglycolate metabolism and photoreduciton of O<sub>2</sub> cooperate in high-light acclimation of <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. strain PCC 6803</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>230</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>637</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-009-0972-9</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinhorst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Murin</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Characterization of the carboxysomal carbonic anhydrase CsoSCA from <italic>Halothiobacillus neapolitanus</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of Bacteriology</source> <volume>188</volume>:<fpage>8087</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8094</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00990-06</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogren</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1981</year>. <article-title>Species variation in the specificity of ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>291</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>515</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/291513a0</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanisms in photosynthetic microorganisms</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>570</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.50.1.539</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aurora</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakrasi</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>Critical roles of bacterioferritins in iron storage and proliferation of cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source> <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>1666</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1673</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.042770</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Penner-Hahn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakrasi</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <article-title>A light-dependent mechanism for massive accumulation of manganese in the photosynthetic bacterium <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. PCC 6803</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>15085</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15092</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi026892s</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Analysis of carboxysomes from <italic>Synechococcus</italic> PCC7942 reveals multiple RuBisCO complexes with carboxysomal proteins CcmM and CcaA</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source> <volume>292</volume>:<fpage>29323</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29335</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M703896200</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2002</year>. <article-title>Novel gene products associated with NdhD3/D4-containing NDH-1 complexes are involved in photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> hydration in the cyanobacterium, <italic>Synechococcus</italic> sp. strain PCC7942</article-title>. <source>Molecular Microbiology</source> <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>435</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.02753.x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahlmann</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahnke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Loosen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Rapid determination of the dry weight of single living cyanobacterial cells using the Mach-Zehnder double-beam interference microscop</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Phyology</source> <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>355</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>364</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09670260802168625</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Elrifi</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Turpin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1989</year>. <article-title>The relationship between ribulose bisphosphate concentration, dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) transport and DIC-limited photosynthesis in cyanobacterium <italic>Synechococcus leopoliensis</italic> grown at different concentrations of inorganic carbon</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source> <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>720</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>727</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.90.2.720</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Staehelin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1979</year>. <article-title>Analysis of thylalkoid outer surface. Coupling factor is limited ot unstacked membrane regions</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source> <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.68.1.30</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Missner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#xfc;gler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Saparov</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathai</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidel</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Carbon dioxide transport through membranes</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</source> <volume>283</volume>:<fpage>25340</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25347</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M800096200</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>Identification of an ATP-binding cassette transporter involved in bicarbonate uptake in the cyanobacterium <italic>Synechococcus</italic> sp strain PCC7942</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>13571</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13576</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.23.13571</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papapostolou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Howorka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Engineering and exploiting protein assemblies in synthetic biology</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biosystems</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>732</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b902440a</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pe&#xf1;a</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Castel</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>de Araujo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Espie</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Structural basis of the oxidative activation of carboxysomal <italic>&#x3b3;</italic>-carbonic anhydrase, CcmM</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>2455</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2460</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <article-title>Inorganic carbon transporters of the cyanobacterial CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism</article-title>. <source>Photosynthesis Research</source> <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>57</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11120-010-9608-y</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1989</year>. <article-title>Expression of human carbonic anhydrase in the cyanobacterium <italic>Synechococcus</italic> PCC7942 creates a high CO<sub>2</sub>-requiring phenotype</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source> <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>505</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>513</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.91.2.505</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodger</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>Advances in understanding the cyanobacterial CO<sub>2</sub>-concentrating-mechanism (CCM): functional components, C<sub>i</sub> transporters, diversity, genetic regulation and prospects for engineering into plants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1441</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1461</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erm112</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodger</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Advances in understanding the cyanobacterial CO<sub>2</sub>-concentrating-mechanism (ccm): functional components, C<sub>i</sub> transporters, diversity, genetic regulation and prospects for engineering into plants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source> <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1441</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1461</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erm112</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultemeyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Klughammer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>The functioning of the CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism in several cyanobacterial strains: a review of general physiological characteristics, genes, proteins, and recent advances</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Botany</source> <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>973</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1001</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b98-081</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodger</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Howitt</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>Identification of a SuIP-type bicarbonate transporter in marine cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>18228</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18233</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0405211101</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosloff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1991</year>. <article-title>A model for inorganic carbon fluxes and photosynthesis in cyanobacterial carboxysomes</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Botany</source> <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>984</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>988</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b91-126</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zviman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1989</year>. <article-title>A quantitative model for inorganic carbon fluxes and photosynthesis in cyanobacterial carboxysomes</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry: PPB</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>945</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>954</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosgaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>de Porcellinis adn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frigaard</surname><given-names>NU</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakuragi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Bioengineering of carbon fixation, biofuels, and biochemcials in cyanobacteria and plants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biotechnology</source> <volume>162</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>147</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2012.05.006</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfonso</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Spatially ordered dynamics of the bacterial carbon fixation machinery</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>327</volume>:<fpage>1258</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1261</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1186090</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tlusty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Cross-species analysis traces adaptation of RuBisCO toward optimality in a low-dimensional landscape</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>3475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3480</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0911663107</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Paredes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Khant</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soyer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Structure of <italic>Halothiobacillus neapolitanus</italic> carboxysomes by cryo-electron tomography</article-title>. <source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source> <volume>364</volume>:<fpage>526</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>535</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2006.09.024</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuzawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <article-title>Distinct constitutive and low-CO<sub>2</sub>-induced CO<sub>2</sub> uptake systems in cyanobacteria: genes involved and their phylogenetic relationship with homologous genes in other organisms</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>11789</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11794</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.191258298</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sultemeyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1995</year>. <article-title>Characterisation of carbon dioxide and bicarbonate transport during steady-state photosynthesis in the marine cyanobacterium <italic>Synechococcus</italic> strain PCC7002</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>197</volume>:<fpage>597</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>607</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00191566</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tcherkez</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Despite slow catalysis and confused substrate specificity, all ribulose bisphosphate carboxylases may be nearly optimized</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>7246</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7251</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0600605103</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchernov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassidim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukenik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <article-title>Sustained net CO<sub>2</sub> evolution during photosynthesis by marin microorganisms</article-title>. <source>Current Biology</source> <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>728</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(06)00330-7</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchernov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>Massive light-dependent cycling of inorganic carbon between oxygenic photosynthetic microorganism and their surroundings</article-title>. <source>Photosynthesis Research</source> <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>103</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1025869600935</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volokita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenvirth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1984</year>. <article-title>Nature of the inorganic carbon species actively taken up by the cyanobacterium <italic>Anabaena variabilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source> <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>599</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>602</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.76.3.599</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Comparing the <italic>in vivo</italic> function of <italic>&#x3b1;</italic>- and <italic>&#x3b2;</italic>- carboxysomes in two model cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source> <volume>165</volume>:<fpage>398</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>411</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.237941</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodger</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Badger</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>Sensing of inorganic carbon limitation in <italic>Synechococcus</italic> PCC7942 is correlated with the size of the internal inorganic carbon pool and involves oxygen</article-title>. <source>Plant Physioogyl</source> <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>1959</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1969</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.069146</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerfeld</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinhorst</surname><given-names>CAK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Protein-based organelles in bacteria: carboxysomes and related microcompartments</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>691</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1913</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawaya</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerfeld</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>Self-assembly in the carboxysome: a viral capsid-like protein shell in bacterial cells</article-title>. <source>Biochemical Society Transactions</source> <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>511</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST0350508</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article article-type="article-commentary" id="SA1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.017</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>Ron</given-names></name><role>Reviewing editor</role><aff><institution>Weizmann Institute for Science</institution>, <country>Israel</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><body><boxed-text><p>eLife posts the editorial decision letter and author response on a selection of the published articles (subject to the approval of the authors). An edited version of the letter sent to the authors after peer review is shown, indicating the substantive concerns or comments; minor concerns are not usually shown. Reviewers have the opportunity to discuss the decision before the letter is sent (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://elifesciences.org/review-process">review process</ext-link>). Similarly, the author response typically shows only responses to the major concerns raised by the reviewers.</p></boxed-text><p>Thank you for sending your work entitled &#x201c;Systems analysis of the carbon concentrating mechanism in cyanobacteria&#x201d; for consideration at <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been favorably evaluated by a Senior editor, Detlef Weigel, and 3 reviewers, one of whom has served as a Guest Reviewing editor.</p><p>The following individuals responsible for the peer review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Ron Milo (guest Reviewing editor); Aaron Kaplan (peer reviewer).</p><p>The Reviewing editor and the other reviewers discussed their comments before we reached this decision, and the Reviewing editor has assembled the following comments to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>The authors build and analyze a model of the carboxysomes in single celled photosynthetic organisms, in order to better understand the role of different aspects of the CO2 concentrating mechanism. Their analysis helps to shed light on the quantitative effect of the parameter values of the participating components and helps clarify the qualitative features leading to functionality in this important mechanism.</p><p>Specifically, the manuscript presents a reaction-diffusion model to capture the interplay between Ci transport into the cell, carboxysome permeability, and the enzymatic activity of carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO. It captures most of the biologically relevant mechanisms (more below). The authors then proceed to solve the model numerically and analytically to solve for Ci concentration as a function of numerous biologically relevant parameters and make a number of intriguing observations. These include: i) identifying a parameter space detailing the interplay between membrane permeability and carboxysome shell permeability, ii) that selectivity of the carboxysome shell is not necessary, iii) there is an optimal non-specific shell permeability, and iv) the hypothesized scavenging of &#x27;lost&#x27; CO2 contributes minimally to fixation capacity.</p><p>Major comments:</p><p>1) Much of the results section is hard to follow until the interpretation is given in the first few sections now given in the discussion. The authors should consider if they could restructure that part of the text to enhance readability of that part. Similarly, some of the motivation and contrasting options that the model sheds light on were clear only after reading the end of the discussion section. In the same spirit it is suggested that a qualitative description of the dynamics leading to CO2 capturing in the carboxysomes should be given in the introduction. This will serve the reader as a mental picture to use in reading the results section.</p><p>2) Is there somewhere a statement on the fate of HCO3 imported into the cell, what fraction is lost back to the outside and what fraction is fixed by Rubisco?</p><p>What is assumed about the concentration of HCO3 outside the cell? Is it constant and if so at what value. If so, can one justly assume that it is not affected by the boundary conditions with the cell surface?</p><p>3) Try to examine the diffusivity of CO2 within the carboxysome taking the packed Rubisco nature into account, vs permeability of the carboxysomal shell; the CO2 concentration in the cytoplasm as judged from membrane inlet mass spectrometer measurements and Ci cycling vs that predicted by the model and analysis of the relative carboxylase/oxygenase activities in an attempt to explain massive formation of glycolate despite the presence of the CCM.</p><p>4) pH will affect every aspect of this biochemical network, from Ci equilibrium to the known sensitivity of RuBisCO to pH. A more thorough explanation of this exclusion is warranted. Additionally, ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate, the other substrate used in the RuBisCO reaction is not mentioned in the manuscript, let alone included in the model. It can be intuitively understand why it may not be relevant, but a cursory explanation should be included.</p><p>5) The value of j_c&#x223c;0.7 cm/s should be compared to what can be realistically expected from molecular/physiological considerations. That is, can you give a sense of what is needed to achieve such a rate given what is known about active transporters rates? Can one make a sanity check on the number of needed transporters on the cell membrane/the fraction of the membrane surface area they will occupy? Here is how I quickly tried to approach it and might have made some error along the way: if the radius of the cell is 0.5 um then the surface area is about 3 um&#x5e;2. With a j_c of 0.7 cm/s&#x3d;0.7x10&#x5e;4 um/s the incoming flux is from an effective volume of &#x223c;2x10&#x5e;4 um&#x5e;3/s. At a concentration of 10mM, equivalent to about 10&#x5e;7 molecules per um&#x5e;3 this leads to &#x223c;10&#x5e;11 molecules/s. This is a vast flux. The energy expenditure to sustain it would be too high. Also, at a turnover rate of say 10&#x5e;3 s-1 per transporter it will require more transporters than the membrane can sustain. The authors can verify my calculation by looking at their SI <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ5">equation 5</xref>, equating alpha&#x3d;0 and C _cytosol&#x3d;0 and then plugging the values for C_our and k_m&#x5e;c and changing the units they will get about 10&#x5e;11 molecules s-1 um-2 which I think transporters cannot accommodate in the membrane. The authors are asked to explain where this line of logic (that seems to suggest that the range of parameters chosen is not realistic) fails.</p></body></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="SA2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02043.018</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><body><p><italic>1) Much of the results section is hard to follow until the interpretation is given in the first few sections now given in the discussion. The authors should consider if they could restructure that part of the text to enhance readability of that part. Similarly, some of the motivation and contrasting options that the model sheds light on were clear only after reading the end of the discussion section. In the same spirit it is suggested that a qualitative description of the dynamics leading to CO2 capturing in the carboxysomes should be given in the introduction. This will serve the reader as a mental picture to use in reading the results section</italic>.</p><p>As suggested, we have updated the last paragraph in the Introduction to give a preview of the conclusions, including the scenarios compared in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>, and a brief qualitative description of how a single carboxysome permeability leads to increase in CO2 levels in the carboxysomes. We have moved the description of why an optimal carboxysome exists from the Discussion section to the Results section.</p><p><italic>2) Is there somewhere a statement on the fate of HCO3 imported into the cell, what fraction is lost back to the outside and what fraction</italic> <italic>is fixed by Rubisco?</italic></p><p><italic>What is assumed about the concentration of HCO3 outside the cell? Is it constant and if so at what value. If so, can one justly assume that it is</italic> <italic>not affected by the boundary conditions with the cell surface?</italic></p><p>We have added a section to the Discussion entitled &#x201c;Are the fluxes and concentrations reasonable?&#x201d; In this section we compare the results of our model to net flux measurements. We also include a version of the following:</p><p>We have produced two tables each for a different rate of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport into the cell. They show the fate of the carbon, in terms of the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leaking out, CO<sub>2</sub> leaking out, CO<sub>2</sub> fixation or carboxylation, and O2 fixation or oxygenation. The assumed concentration of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> outside the cell is 14.9&#x03BC;M. Other parameters are held constant and their values are provided in the tables in the text (moved from the supplement). Whether the transport of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the cell greatly effects the external HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration will depend on whether the cell is in a &#x201c;well mixed&#x201d; environment or whether there is no replenishment of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>. We have assumed that the cell is in a well-mixed environment such that the external HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration is constant.<fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Author response table 1.</label><graphic xlink:href="elife02043f007"/></fig><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Author response table 2.</label><graphic xlink:href="elife02043f008"/></fig></p><p>To determine whether these rates are reasonable, we can calculate the density of transporters necessary to achieve this level of flux (see last response). We can also calculate the grams of carbon fixed per cell per hour. From the tables, at an HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport rate of <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 0.7cm/s, the carboxylation rate is 8.78 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup> picomoles/s &#x3d; 3.16<sup>&#x2212;3</sup> picomoles/hour. Given the mass of carbon (12 g/mol), this is 0.14 picograms/hour. A similar calculation for the carboxylation rate given a lower flux (in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>) results in 0.014 picograms/hour. A cyanobacterial cell is about 48% carbon by weight, and have a dry mass weight of 23&#x2013;-600 femtograms/&#x03BC;m<sup>3</sup>. So between 115-300 femtograms/&#x03BC;m<sup>3</sup> of carbon are needed to produce a new cyanobacterial cell. Our model cell has a volume of 0.52&#x03BC;m<sup>3</sup>, so we need between 0.1 and 0.3 picograms of carbon per cell. At the higher flux rate this means that a cell could replicate every 1-2hrs, so faster than cyanobacteria replicate. At a the lower flux rate though, a new cell worth of carbon is fixed every 8 to 21hrs, which is similar to the division times of cyanobacteria!</p><p>A substantial amount of carbon brought into the cell is lost through leakage, mostly in the form of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>. According to our calculation only around 1% of the carbon transported into the cell is fixed into 3-phosophoglycerate. However, the production of 2-phosphoglycolate is reduced by an order of magnitude from the low to high flux rate. In no case is it completely reduced with 1000 2-phosophoglycolate produced per second even at the high flux rate.</p><p><italic>In the model it is assumed that the carbonic anhydrase is distributed throughout the carboxysome, however it has been found to be localized to the inside the carboxysome shell. How would organization of the carbonic anhydrase to only a thin layer</italic> <italic>around the carboxysome shell effect the results?</italic></p><p>We explored the effect of localizing the carbonic anhydrase to a thin layer on the inside of the carboxysome shell, from Rc &#x3d; 500 nm &#x3e; r &#x3e; 450 nm. The RuBisCO is localized to the inner region of the carboxysome and does not overlap with the carbonic anhydrase. The total amount of carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO remain the same between the case with organization inside the carboxysome and case where both enzymes are evenly distributed throughout the carboxysome (with a higher concentration in the localized cases). So, there is no change in the overall carbonic anhydrase or RuBisCO activity, only in the location. We also show the organized and unorganized cases for two diffusion constants in the carboxysome (<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup> cm/s and <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup> cm/s).</p><p>The location of the enzymes in the carboxysome has no effect on the resulting CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration, since the carboxysome is so small. The time it takes for a CO<sub>2</sub> or HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> molecule to diffuse across the carboxysome is the same order of mag- nitude as, or smaller than, the reaction rate of carbonic anhydrase. The difference in concentration across the carboxsome is less than 1% change. This effect would become larger if diffusion were extremely slow. These effects do not support suggestions that carbonic anhydrase localization to the carboxysome shell could act to facilitate transport of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the carboxysome by locally decreasing the HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration. We updated the text to mention these results in the discussion section entitled &#x201c;Concentration profiles of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, and include the figure in the supplementary information.<fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Author response image 1.</label><caption><p>No effect of localizing carbonic anhydrase to the shell of the carboxysome. We assume the same amount of carbonic anhydrase and RuBisCO activity for each simulation and compare the case with the enzymes evenly distributed throughout the carboxysome to the case where the carbonic anhydrase is localized to the inner carboxysome shell. The (-.-) lines are for no organization and (x) for localization with <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup> cm/s. The (...) lines are for no organization and (o) are for localization with <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup> cm/s.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife02043f009"/></fig></p><p><italic>3) Try to examine the diffusivity of CO2 within the carboxysome taking the packed Rubisco nature into account, vs permeability of the carboxysomal shell; the CO2 concentration in the cytoplasm as judged from membrane inlet mass spectrometer measurements and Ci cycling vs that predicted by the model and analysis of the relative carboxylase/oxygenase activities in an attempt to explain massive formation of glycolate despite the presence of the CCM</italic>.</p><p>We have explored the effect of decreased diffusion for CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> in the carboxysome. We show the phase space for HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport and carboxysome permeability assuming a diffusion constant two orders of magnitude smaller, or appropriate for diffusion of small molecules in a 60% sucrose solution (viscosity is increased by a factor of 100 [Iscotables]). We find that a decreased diffusion constant does indeed increase the optimal value of carboxysome permeability. However, for all values of carboxysome permeability, a higher HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport rate is required to achieve the same CO<sub>2</sub> concentration with the lower diffusion constant. This effect is most prominent near the carboxysome permeability calculated from geometric arguments in the text. For high carboxysome permeabilities the decrease in diffusion constant has only a small negative effect. Therefore, a lower diffusion constant in the carboxysome has primarily a negative impact on the effectiveness of the CCM.</p><p>We have updated the manuscript to mention these results in the Discussion section entitled &#x201c;Concentration profiles of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup>, and include the figure in the supplementary information.<fig id="fig10" position="float"><label>Author response image 2.</label><caption><p>Phase space for HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport and carboxysome permeability. Solid lines show lines of constant CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the carboxysome for <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 1e &#x2212; 5 cm<sup>2</sup>/s, or the diffusion constant of small molecule in water. Dashed lines show the same lines of constant CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, bur for <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 1e &#x2212; 7 cm<sup>2</sup>/s, or the diffusion constant of a small molecule in a 60% sucrose solution.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="elife02043f010"/></fig></p><p><italic>Comment on cycling to dissipate light energy &#x2013; contrary to assumption of not wasting energy when carbonic anhydrase is saturated</italic>.</p><p>Certainly there could be other functions of the components of the CCM besides concentrating CO<sub>2</sub> around RuBisCO. We constrain our modeling efforts to describing the necessary components for efficient CO<sub>2</sub> fixation. We have updated the text to include a comment on cycling to dissipate light energy as a possible benefit of the scavenging and CO<sub>2</sub> uptake mechanism.</p><p><italic>Also comment on the relative carboxylase/oxygenase activities in an attempt to explain massive formation of glycolate despite the presence of the CCM</italic>.</p><p>One of the main arguments of our work is that the CCM can raise the concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> in the carboxysome, but cannot completely remove O<sub>2</sub>. Improving the ratio of CO<sub>2</sub> to O<sub>2</sub> in the carboxysome reduces the rate of glycolate formation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref> in the text specifically addresses the proportion of oxygenase activity to carboxylase activity. We show that even at optimal carboxysome permeability there will be 3 glycolate formed for every 1000 carboxylation reactions. We have updated the discussion section &#x201c;Are the fluxes and concentrations reasonable?&#x201d; to more clearly discuss these results.</p><p><italic>Additionally, ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate, the other substrate used in the RuBisCO reaction is not mentioned in the manuscript, let alone included in the model. It can be intuitively understand why it may not be relevant, but a cursory explanation should be included</italic>.</p><p>We have updated the description of the RuBisCO reaction in the &#x201c;Reaction diffusion model&#x201d; section to mention ribulous-1,5-bisphosphate, and explain why we do not include it in the model. It has been shown that under low exgternal carbon concentrations all RuBisCO sites are saturated by ribulous-1,5-bisphosphate, and the carboxylation reactions are limited only by CO<sub>2</sub>.</p><p><italic>4) pH will affect every aspect of this biochemical network, from Ci equilibrium to the known sensitivity of RuBisCO to pH. A more thorough explanation of this exclusion is warranted</italic>.</p><p>We have added a section entitled &#x201c;Effects of pH&#x201d; in the discussion section and include the following: We agree that all enzymes in the CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism are sensitive to pH. Cyanobacteria must regulate pH within the cell, and we have not attempted to model this regulation. While we do not explicitly include the dependence of the reaction rates to pH, they are implicitly included in the selection of the reaction rates. The effect of pH can been understood by examining the effect of changing the reaction rates. While we did not spend time exploring varying reaction rates in the paper, the dependence can be found in the analytic solutions given in the supplementary information.</p><p>For example the reaction rate of RuBisCO will determine whether there exists a region where a non-specific carboxysome shell can increase the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration around RuBisCO. If the RuBisCO reaction rate is fast enough it could overwhelm the rate at which HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> diffuses into the carboxysome. However, if RuBisCO were faster (and also less oxygen sensitive) then the cyanobacteria would have already solved problem of maximizing carbon fixation and not need the CO<sub>2</sub> concentrating mechanism to begin with!</p><p>The equilibrium ratio of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub> is also sensitive to pH. To understand the effect on the carbon concentrating mechanism, we must treat the outside of the cell, cytosol, and carboxysome regions separately. We have analyzed the effect of pH outside the cell by exploring the carbon uptake under various external inorganic carbon ratios (shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). In the cytosol the pH will have little effect on the CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> levels, since the concentrations are being held out of equilibrium. In other words, transport of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the cell, leakage or recycling of CO<sub>2</sub> and diffusion are all much faster than the equilibration reactions of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> due to pH and therefore their levels are set by all other processes. Inside the carboxysome however, carbonic anhydrase does bring the CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the equilibrium set by the pH. Therefore their ratio in the carbonic anhydrase unsaturated regime will be set entirely by the pH inside the carboxysome. We have discussed this briefly in the analysis of the model.</p><p>It has been suggested that the CO<sub>2</sub> facilitated uptake mechanism functions by creating alkaline pockets at the thylakoid membrane. Diffusion of hydrogen ions across the cell would be very fast, so such pockets would require massive reduction from the light reactions to maintain local alkalinity. We have simplified the treatment of these mechanisms as well, by simply assuming some enzmatic activity that converts CO<sub>2</sub> to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> at the cell membrane.</p><p><italic>5) The value of j_c&#x223c;0.7 cm/s should be compared to what can be realistically expected from molecular/physiological considerations. That is, can you give a sense of what is needed to achieve such a rate given what is known about active transporters rates? Can one make a sanity check on the number of needed transporters on the cell membrane/the fraction of the membrane surface area they will occupy? Here is how I quickly tried to approach it and might have made some error along the way: if the radius of the cell is 0.5 um then the surface area is about 3 um&#x5e;2. With a j_c of 0.7 cm/s&#x3d;0.7x10&#x5e;4 um/s the incoming flux is from an effective volume of &#x223c;2x10&#x5e;4 um&#x5e;3/s. At a concentration of 10mM, equivalent to about 10&#x5e;7 molecules per um&#x5e;3 this leads to &#x223c;10&#x5e;11 molecules/s. This is a vast flux. The energy expenditure to sustain it would be too high. Also, at a turnover rate of say 10&#x5e;3 s-1 per transporter it will require more transporters than the membrane can sustain. The authors can verify my calculation by looking at their SI</italic> <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ5"><italic>equation 5</italic></xref><italic>, equating alpha&#x3d;0 and C _cytosol&#x3d;0 and then plugging the values for C_our and k_m&#x5e;c and changing the units they will get about 10&#x5e;11 molecules s-1 um-2 which I think transporters cannot accommodate in the membrane. The authors are asked to explain where this line of logic (that seems to suggest that the range of parameters chosen is not realistic) fails</italic>.</p><p>We include a version of the following discussion in the &#x201c;Are the fluxes and concentrations reasonable?&#x201d; section of the text. We are assuming that we are under inorganic carbon limiting conditions. Under these conditions it has been shown that the carbon dioxide concentrating mechanism is upregulated, including transport of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> into the cell. Under low inorganic carbon levels (15 &#x03BC;M) the carbon dioxide concenting mechanism achieves the highest amplification of internal to external inorganic carbon (a factor of about 1000), and internal inorganic carbon pools are measured around (30 mM).</p><p>The appropriate value for determining the flux of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> from active transport at the surface is <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub><italic>H</italic><sub><italic>out</italic></sub> &#x3d; (0.7cm/s)(15&#x03BC;M) &#x3d; (0.7cm/s)(15 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;9</sup>mol/cm3) &#x3d; 1 &#xd7; 10<sup>&#x2212;8</sup>mols<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>cm<sup>&#x2212;2</sup>, not using the value of 10mM as was suggested by the reviewer. (We realize that we had unclearly referenced several inorganic carbon concentrations without indicating whether they were internal or external, we have sought to clarify in the text.) The surface area of the cell is <italic>SA</italic> &#x3d; <italic>4&#x03C0;R</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> &#x3d; 4&#x03C0;(5&#xd7;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup>cm)<sup>2</sup> &#x3d; 3&#xd7;10<sup>&#x2212;8</sup>cm<sup>2</sup>. So that&#x2019;s a flux of 3&#xd7;10<sup>&#x2212;16</sup>mol/s &#x3d; 2&#xd7;10<sup>7</sup><italic>molecules/s</italic>. Assuming the rate of transport per trans- porter suggested by the reviewer, 10<sup>3</sup><italic>molecules/s</italic> this requires 10<sup>4</sup><italic>transporters/cell</italic> or 10<sup>3</sup><italic>transporters/&#x03BC;m</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>. This is actually not that far off from the number of ATP synthase complexes on the thylakoid membrane in spinach, 700<italic>complexes/&#x03BC;m</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> (bionumbers &#x23;107018), although it is still quite high.</p><p>We have selected our <italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> value specifically to produce a 30mM internal HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration consistent with experimentally measured values. (HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> is the dominate form of inorganic carbon in the cell &#x2013; as has been shown experimentally.) In fact the internal HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration is dependent almost entirely on the transporter activity (jc) and the permeability of the cell membrane. This lack of sensitivity to carboxysome permeability for example can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, as the location of the grey line (<italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x3d; 0.7cm/s) varies little with carboxysome permeability. Similarly the amount of which is consumed in reaction is very small. The internal HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> concentration is set by the flux into the cell (<italic>j</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub><italic>H</italic><sub><italic>out</italic></sub>) being approximately equal to the amount of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leaking back out of the cell (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub><sup><italic>H</italic></sup> (<italic>H</italic><sub><italic>cytosol</italic></sub> &#x2212; <italic>H</italic><sub><italic>out</italic></sub>))<fig id="fig11" position="float"><label>Author response equation 1.</label><graphic xlink:href="elife02043f011"/></fig></p><p>This resulting number is smaller than the value calculated in the text because we have neglected carbon fixation and leakage from CO<sub>2</sub>. Both of these effects require an additional flux of &#x2248; 0.1cm/s to maintain according to our calculations.</p><p>Therefore, if the calculated transport rate is too high, one must call into question either the measurements of the concentrating power of CCM and internal carbon pools, or the permeability of the cell membrane. It should be pointed out that this enormous flux is only expected to occur under extremely low external inorganic carbon conditions, when the CCM is up-regulated. It is tempting to argue that perhaps the multiple membranes in cyanobacteria greatly decrease the effective permeability of the cell membrane. If this is true, and these membranes act as a barrier to HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> leakage, then there must also be active HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport into the cell at these membranes, or else they would detrimentally restrict HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x2212;</sup> transport into the cell.</p></body></sub-article></article>
